Hello, welcome everyone. It's April 9th,
2025 and we're here in active inference
gueststream 102.1 with Majid Benny and
Dean as well. So we're looking forward
to a presentation and a discussion on
scientific explanation, causality and
agency, a free energy account. Thank you
Majid for joining again. Looking forward
to the presentation and go for it.
All right. Thank you very much for
inviting me. It's great to be here and
uh I'm going to cut to the chase and
start to introduce the project to speak
about the project. So uh scientific
explanation causality and agency is the
name of the book and you can see the
image uh in the next page. uh well it's
it's a 2024 book by Rott
and so I'm going to briefly speak about
the main themes of the book uh it is
about the agency
uh in the next page uh sorry to uh to
just interrupting by saying the next
page but it is an aspect of my book so
uh it's uh it tries to develop a
philosophical articulation of agency See
in terms of the free energy principle so
I presume most people who are uh
watching this or listening to this are
familiar with the free energy principle
which has been developed by Carl Fristen
and colleagues and uh provides an
account of perception cognition and
action in terms of minimization of uh uh
free energy principle which is an
information theoretic threshold uh an
upper bound on surprisal or prediction
error.
And uh so agency agents are
self-organizing systems and uh but a
particular kind of self organizing
systems. They have this pec peculiar
capacity to minimalize not only their
free energy but their expected free
energy or the free energy that is
associated with the
uh future sequences of action on the
basis of their evaluation of
counterfactual outcomes of their action.
So other people have been doing that. Of
course, uh Carl Freeston himself and his
colleagues have been working on this
theory of agency and a number of other
significant people such as
um um Andy Clark for example amongst
others have been developing a theories
of agency in terms of the free energy
principle.
So I delved a bit more deeper in this
respect and tried to provide a more uh
specific and clear identification of
agency in terms of the free energy
principle but it is u not the main
contribution of the work as I said this
this book as I said other people have
been trying to do that. So the main
contribution of the uh book is to try to
cast philosophy of science, theories of
causality and scientific explanation and
causal uh causal explanation in terms of
this uh uh theory of agency in terms of
the free energy principle. So and this
is something that uh I have uh I'm going
to discuss in the next page of this
slide. So the next slide is about the
main contribution of the uh of this uh
of this book. So it uh there there have
been theories of science
for since for uh at least for scientific
realist is basically about scientific
explanation. Science aims at explain
explaining things and there have been
causal theories of explanation for a
while. No, this book tries to instead of
treating causal scientific
explanation as something that is totally
objective and totally
avoidant structure of the world. It
tries to cast causal explanation in
terms of
uh
agents models of their environment and
agents are specified in terms of the
free energy principle. So uh and there
are a number of interesting
philosophical questions here at least
interesting for me. So whether this kind
of causal explanation are building on
some sort of totally objective
conception of causality or it is
something that is projected from the
mind of agents onto the world and it is
the
uh the account that I'm defending in
this book the projectivist account and
I'm supporting that on the basis of the
free energy principle at the same time I
do not think that it
necessarily undermines is realist
commitments to the co uh to re realist
commitments that might be associated
with causal
explanations. Uh
because by the very fact that this
theory tries to support its accounts of
scientific explanation by the best
scientific theories or at least the most
progressive scientific theories of the
field. It comes with degrees of uh uh
objectivity. It it bestows upon its
theories a degree of objectivity that
might be otherwise
uh missing from theory of explanation.
So
uh in the next slide I'm referring to
the philosophical background of this
proposal. So and the proposal could be I
mean the project of the book is
ambitious at the same time it might be
uh a bit confusing because it tries to
bring together two different cultures.
So there is free energy principle and
philosophy of mind and cognitive
science. So philosopher, philosophers of
mind and cognitive science are more or
less quite familiar with free energy
principle uh Beijian theories of
cognition and this kind of a stuff and
they try to explore its uh implication
ramifications for
uh theories of perceptual
representation, cognition, action, self
consciousness whatever. On the other
hand, there is philosophy of science and
there is uh philosophy of action and
there is philosophy of causation and
philosophy of
explanation. Uh so people who are
working in cognitive science or people
who are working on philosophical aspects
of free energy principle are not always
I mean are not necessarily interested in
that kind of philosophy or philosophy of
science and philosophers of science
usually are not that uh that that much
concerned with progress in
uh cognitive sciences. There have been
philosophers of science, good
philosophers of science who have been
concerned with progress in in
in cognitive sciences. I'm thinking of
uh Paul Churchland and Ron Giri and uh
and Narcission and so on. But more
recently, philosophers of science are
started to philosophy of science started
to move to other directions. But this
this uh branch of philosophy of science
that sets the stage for my agentic
theory of causality is u manipulability
theory originally uh developed by
pragmatist and then uh advanced by Hugh
Price and Peter Menses and uh James
Woodward and others and it tried to
account for causality. there have been
there has been a agency theory of
causality and then I developed that into
agency theory of explanation as well.
Um and it is a more or less well
established theory in philosophy of
science or at least it has been a very
well established uh theory in philosophy
of science for in
1990s and for two decades but it became
a bit overshadowed by manipulability
theory and interventionism.
uh but I did try
to cast this theory in terms of uh
advancement in cognitive science in
terms of free energy principle and so
on. Uh so which has been more or less an
in innovative move and then came with
some ramifications that that even I
didn't think of when I started to
develop the project. So next slide
speaks about price projects. I don't
think that we need to
uh to uh dwell on that. And I'm moving
to the next slide on the central role of
the free energy principle in my
project. So
uh yeah uh philosophers of science
sometimes rely on scientific
advancement. So of course philosophers
of physics are always concerned but by
with what happens in physics modern
physics and philosophers of cognitive
science are concerned with what happened
in cognitive science but I'm what I'm
trying to do in this project is to go
beyond that and use free energy
principle as a framework for
uh
for embedding entrenching my theory of
philosophy of science or my philosophy
of science in the sense that
uh I see science as something that takes
place by cognitive agents by cognitive
self-organizing systems both
individually and collectively and then I
think that free energy principle with
its account of how self-organizing
systems model the environment to
themselves and
uh use these models to steer in the
world to to fair and make decisions and
so on and and prosper provides a good
basis for
uh uh for a theory of philosophy of
science. And then it comes with some
sort of
projectivism which is uh again a view
that has been defended by
uh Hugh
Price before but uh interestingly enough
it finds a nice counterpart in free
energy principle and its account of
hierarchical organization of
minimization of free energy and how
cognition starts from generative models
in the top levels of these organizations
and then how cognition and perception
take place when the agents try to
project these models onto the world and
then uh minimize the discrepancy between
these models by either acting on the
world or or updating their
models.
So yeah, so the next slide is also about
projectivism. We can return to that
later, but I'm going to wrap up quickly
because I want to leave more time to uh
discussion. So I go to the slide about
the book's
structure.
Uh so uh early chapters of the book set
their stage. So the first chapter
describes the project of the book in
which it try and and and its attempt to
uh to outline a humanistic perspective
on causality and scientific explanation
and how uh free energy principle plays a
role. And the second second chapter is
about the free energy
principle. I provide an articulation of
the free energy principle. I also
explain in what sense I'm a structural
realist about free energy principle and
what justifies my realism about the free
energy principle. Then uh there is a
substantive chapter on agents and agency
and how agency could be specified in
terms of the free energy principle
uh and how free energy principle could
be used to set a distin to model
different kinds of entities and then set
a distinction between them in terms of
levels of
complexity. Uh then later chapters deal
with some more specific technical
notions and concepts in philosophy of
science.
such as modern realism where I try to
uh yeah deconstruct modalities in terms
of counterfactual model making in the uh
regenerative model or generative models
of agents and uh some other topics such
as
uh
the progress of science and scientific
pra practice in terms of the
collaboration between humans and
artifacts or how science and scientific
representation is something that takes
place in the networks of collaboration
of human humans and human artifacts and
also some other technical notions and
yeah perhaps technical is not the right
term perennial notions in philosophy of
science such as physical alism and non
physicalism and so on. And I think that
this is the last slide that I'm going to
discuss and then open the floor to
discussions which provides a sketch of
the chapters of the book. And
no, it's the time for me
to wait for your input and your
demonstration of your master of your
your your superior understanding of the
content of my work.
Dean, you've never been set up like
this. I
know. So machine I I've got about five
questions and I hope all of them don't
give away because my my first suggestion
to anybody watching today is go go go
buy this book and read it because I
think you'll come
away changed because I think it just
brings up so many different ideas that
people probably have never contemplated
and you've made it available whereas I
don't think that was necessarily
something um that existed before you set
out on
this on on completing this work. But my
first question two point first question
I just wanted to say that you're too
coined. Thank you very much. Okay. Well,
I don't think so. Anyway, the strategy
for pushing theories that are typically
within the mind out into the world.
Is there is there some was there some
hope on your part to address that
question because there's a lot of stuff
in here
around sort of coming up with
strategies. So I I'm wondering like when
you were when you were sort of laying
out the outline of this, was that one of
your goals was to sort of speak to how
things within that umbrella of agency
are then are then tested by sort of the
the
environment acting as a scrutiner on on
what we can hold up as objective versus
subjective.
Very
well. Very well. So yeah, it's it's a
very fundamental question. I try to
answer that. I I I
I may uh start to to to delve into too
much details about the history of
philosophy of science, but I think that
uh it gives me the necessary vocabulary,
the jargon to answer to your question.
So look uh when we speak of theories
bringing theories from the mind to the
world and test them and so on. Uh look
philosophy of science in a sense started
with this concern with theories. What
are these theories? How they are tested
and so on. And this this was what have
been happening for a very long time uh
in in the early 20th century uh in works
of logical positivist and so on. and uh
the the the term scientific theory and
its logical implications. I do not want
to del too much into logic and how
theories have been uh understood. So
there uh there the the the contemporary
conception of theory that I'm familiar
with comes from
uh a number of eligible and very good
philosopher works of a number of
eligible and very good philosophers of
science such as Patrick Soups uh Bosman
Frosten uh Steven French Hans Halverson
so they used to see theories as
representation
of phenomena regardless of whether you
consider this phenomena as as parts of
the structure of the real world mind
independent world or or just as
experiences and so on. Uh
uh and and there is a very vast
literature on that and very interesting
uh debate. uh what has been uh a bit
underestimated I mean people there have
been of course also people to consider
that as I said such as Ron Gary and
others but what has been underestimated
a bit was that these theories I are the
byproduct of the cognitive cognitive
agents which are basically
self-organizing systems that are evolved
in this world and and and are systems
that are are are are having this
specific perceptual and cognitive
faculties that they have in order to be
able to
uh to maximize their chance of survival
in in in the evolutionary context and
evolutionary condition but theories have
not been used in this specific terms. So
uh on the other hand there is free
energy principle uh which speaks about
generative models and hypothesis about
the words that are cast in these
generative models and then
self-organizing systems try to check the
veracity or re reliability of these
models against the evidence that they
get from the environment and so on. But
it seems to be some sort of yeah it
seems that there are two different
cultures. People who speak about
theories in science in philosophy on
science and people who speak about
hypothesis or models in cognitive
science as the tools that modeling tools
for the cognitive structure of the uh
cognitive system and brain of
self-organizing system. They it seems
that they are speaking in two different
culture. uh so I'm interested in trying
to ground the uh traditional technical
concept of theories in philosophy of
science in this uh uh more
uh practical more scientific notion of
hypothesis and models as the tools that
self-organizing systems are using to be
able to represent their environment to
themselves and then use them to be able
to fair in the war to be able to to
interact with the with their environment
successfully enough to
uh maximize their chance of survival for
a while at least. So and it is it is a
very complicated because the relation is
reciprocal. So in a way of course the
way that that that Carl Festston and
others speak of models and hypothesises
they are using Beijianism which is
basically a part of science. So there's
a reciprocal relation between one notion
of theories which is quite which is
quite uh theoretical and the other
notion of models which is also
theoretical but is used to represent
some uh embodied mechanisms and
processes in cognitive systems. So I'm
not trying to just ground the the scient
the the philosophical notion of theories
and models into the Beijian notion of
theories of models but the embodied
processes embodied cognitive processes
that are represented by these models in
a nutshell I'm trying to see this
philosophical notion of theories to
grown this philosophical notion of
theories into embodied mechanisms of
interaction of organisms with their
environment. So in that sense yes I
think that theories are things that are
basically grounded in the cognitive
system of self-organizing systems and
they are tested in this fashion and so
on and I think that this sophisticated
notion of uh theory testing
falsification confirmation scientific
explanation
uh and so on and so forth they all could
be explicated and explained on the basis
of this embodied mechanisms of
interaction of individual uh organ
organisms as well as the commodities and
groups of organisms with their
environment and with one
another. Does it answer to your to your
point at all? I mean, and it Yeah. And
it sets up my perfectly my next
question.
So we we're all I think we're all
probably familiar with the with the
expression philosophy of science which
is which is basically an an something
that's familiar established
um and is also an entailment like one of
those things grips the other. Um here's
my next question.
If I if I if I come at the problem after
reading your book and th the book
actually made me ask these questions.
This is what I this is what is how a
this is what what a scientist or how a
scientist thinks. So I set that down
over here. This is what a
philosopher thinks or how a philosopher
thinks. Set that down over here. Left me
with a question after reading the book.
So, what title should we self-escribe or
self-organize if we're between those two
worlds?
Oh, is that is that place nonhyphenated?
Because that that's what you got me
thinking about
through doing this this exploration.
Very
good. Uh yeah. So perhaps it it is a bit
of my personal take in philosophy. So I
do not see philosophy of science as to
different things. I think that uh so so
again perhaps I'm too much uh fascinated
or perhaps fooled by my my own ideas
about everything started from embodied
mechanisms and so on. But I think that
there are basically two problems. What's
the nature of the world and what's the
nature of the mind? uh which could be in
a way one problem if you are interested
in scientific representation and how
mind represent the world and I think
that most of the intellectual
enterprises in the world uh being
scientific or philosophical are
organized around these two main question
the nature of the world and the nature
of the mind. So, uh, some people engage
in more formalism, more
experimentation. Uh, I I think that did
we did we did we lose Dean
briefly possibly.
All right. I I I we pause pause there.
Let me ask another question from the
live chat and and he'll join. Okay. All
right. Uh Susan Hasty wrote, "Is
manipulation
theory another category of control
theory or a
child?" So how would you relate
manipulability theories to control
theory?
I do not know in which context we are
speaking of control theory. I mean some
manipulability theory by manipulability
theory because because there are control
accounts of thermodynamics for example
as opposed to resource theories of
thermodynamics. So I do not know about
the context or the background but the
way that I was using manipulability
theory actually the way that Hugh Price
and James Woodbart and others were using
manipulability theory and it was coming
from the context of uh pragmatism. So
causation and causal relations how to
define them how so so u I think that
people at least since aristo people were
trying to define causation causation
causality and cause effect relation. So
uh this tradition defines causation in
terms of manipulability. In terms of if
you want to know what is causing what
what is bringing about what start to
manipulate what you think is the cause
and see whether there would be any
changes in the set of your effect. So it
manipulability. So and and James
Woodward has has has developed that in
terms of interventionist theories of
causation which can be represented and
modeled in terms of uh for example
amongst other things could be
represented in terms of uh u marovian
networks and marovian blankets and so on
marovian chains uh but uh and and then
there could be a relation between this
and control but I do not know the
context in which uh uh our audience was
mentioning control.
Perfect. After the seventh inning
stretch, Dean is back on the plate. Or
Majid, pick up from where you were on
Dean's question or or Sorry about that,
guys. I have no idea where we were. I I
I
totally continue on. Yeah. Science
science and philosophy. So what I was
trying to say is that yeah I I think uh
this is something that I learned from of
course the tradition of philosophy of
science in which I was brought up which
are works of ro carap and villard venor
coin but also something that I learned
from my uh friend and mentor Steven
French. So I think that philosophy is
best when it is informed by science. Uh
and science some people would say is
best when when it is informed by
philosophy. I'm a bit skeptical about
the latter. So because there are
different philosophies and I don't know
how science could be informed by
philosophy precisely but I think that
philosophy is best when informed by
science in the sense that in my opinion
philosophers and scientists are
basically working on the same topic the
nature of the world and the nature of
mind and so on. Uh so scientists are
usually focusing more on
experimentation. Some scientists
theorical scientists are focusing a bit
more on modeling the consequences of
experimentation or their uh the the uh
theorical context that is necessary for
being able to do this kind of
experimentation at all.
So but none of these people are
necessarily interested in
uh the shape that this experimentation
and theories make of the world. So we
are living in a world we like to know
what are the features of this world how
it looks like what is actually there and
how or or or concept or or or conception
of what we think is there is justified
and philosophers are people who are
trying to engage with this set of latter
questions this set of final questions.
which is which makes sense from my
perspective because we are all some sort
of self-organizing systems collaborating
with one another or to state it in
another where we are just parts of a a
self-organizing network parts so
scientists philosophers and other
intellectual parts of a self-organizing
system uh whose parts are interacting
with one another so it is in a way
natural to have similar concerns but we
are engaging uh so so much as the
division of labor is concerned we are
doing this we are engaging with these
questions at different levels of
generality. So experimentalists for
example are engaging with very detailed
experimentation. Theoreticians
are engaging with them at a higher level
of generality and philosophers are
basically in my opinion people who are
trying to unpack the uh ontological
existential and and epistemological
ramifications of this engagement with
these questions in the sense of trying
to work out. So and this is what I was
trying to do. So uh Carl Priston and
others were were developing this
fascinating framework and I was just
getting interested to know uh what would
be the philosophical ramifications in
the sense that what would be the
universe that we are living in assuming
that what they say about the nature of
self-organizing system is true and and
what implication it would have for the
way that we garner knowledge about
environment and the justification of
those pieces of knowledge and so on.
If it's okay, I'd like to ask one last
question. I apologize. I do not know why
one of my laptops shut down. It's got
lots of battery, but fortunately I have
a backup. So, um my last question and
and this one has a has a bit of a
historical
uh context to it. So, I think it was
2022, we were on a live stream together
and we were talking about
instrumentalism versus an action and
stuff like that. And I think essentially
at that point we were we were kind of
agreeing on the fact that you kind of
need an understanding of both. Kind of
like you need an understanding of
philosophy and and an understanding of
science.
What I'm what I'm really curious about
um my my active engagement with the
active entrance lab and then the
institute started out with a question
around where do we place the emphasis in
terms of ontology and I know in your
book you have made it very clear uh
where where you think ontology fits into
this
um triangulation between uh pragmatism
and free energy principle and agency
theory. Do you mind kind of
sharing how you got to the place where
you well maybe first sharing what your
what you think the emphasis on ontology
should be and then maybe explain how you
how you got there.
Very well. Very well. I I I think that I
remember the moment when we were
discussing in in in in a previous
uh uh event and I think that I see your
point. So uh let me also start to share
a bit of personal history. I I think
that I'm basically a philosopher of
science in the sense that uh I spend a
lot of time about uh pondering the
questions of realism and anti-realism in
experimentalism in philosophy of science
and what struck me what didn't strike me
as odd when I was pondering this
question was that how much reput
reputation do this debate include so
there are people who are antalist and
just uh state their point and offer some
uh some arguments and then realist
defend their point on the basis of some
arguments and there is of this this is
of course a
a a very vibrant tradition. So there is
of course some always some progress but
there is also loads of repetition in the
sense that you rarely notice a totally
new or totally
convincing new argument for either of
these positions. Yeah. At some point I I
started to wonder what would be
uh the point of
taking a straightforward and unshakable
stance on realism or anterialism and
selfidentify as a as a tag bearing
realist or realist.
uh I thought that it would be in a way
incompatible with commitment to
naturalism in the sense that you try to
uh develop this this
uh organic connection between science
and philosophy and try to inform them
with one another. So and science is
always about. So when I say that there
hasn't been that much progress or new
ideas in realist debate, I particularly
compare that with science and progress
in scientific field and and and and and
the diversity of new arguments and new
evidence that is most of the time com
considered in different scientific
fields.
uh and I think that this is something
that I find interesting when I say that
I try I I take free energy principle as
a framework
uh into which I can cast my philosophy
of science. This is what I mean that you
don't need to take uh a rigid stance on
realism or anti-realism. You don't need
to take a general and rigid sense or but
you can focus on a specific topics, a
specific arguments and then see where
they take you and how much uh realist
commitment you would be ready to invest
in those specific claims and theories on
the basis of the evidence that you find
for this these theories these arguments
and ideas at any given moment. So this
evidential decision theory has been a
part of this this this agency approach
to causality that I uh that I revive
that I defend but at the same time uh
the relation between hypothesis and
evidence and trying to explain it to
find evidence for one's existence in
terms of Carl Priston and Jakobi and
then try to always update your
hypothesis on the basis of the new
evidence that you find and so on. I
think that it can a dynamic version of
realism or no realism for that matter
could be could be uh developed on the
basis of that idea. I do not care about
so again I think that this is something
that you price said somewhere. It is not
about being realist or a a nonrealist
but about being not being a naive
realist or a non known known realist.
And I think that free energy principle
provides the opportunity for this
sophistication in the sense that you can
see all of this in terms of a
hierarchical structure of minimizing
your errors, minimizing your predict or
prediction errors of your commitments.
And then you can consider the evidence
that you have and the the possibility
for being able to make to to take a
specific statement a specific model as
the locos of your ontological and
epistemic commitments and then try to do
that rationally on the basis of this
this this opportunity. So it is possible
it would be possible to cast that in
terms of for Beijian updating of course
but I do not think that it needs to make
commitment to a specific formalism even
so much as you are ready to make
concession on revising not only your
theories in terms of new evidence but
also your your commitments realist
commitment in light of the new evidence
that you receive. I think that this
would be a more dynamic and and and a
bit more sophisticated version of a
philosophical stance on science than the
traditional versions of realism or non
realism. So in a way I don't I I don't
in in this in this sense I do not think
that the interesting debate
philosophical debate about free energy
principle is about being realist or
instrumentalist about free energy
principle but taking free energy
principle itself as something that
allows you to regulate the uh real the
the the uh the weight of your realist
commitment or the weight of your
ontological and epistem mological
commitment with regard to any scientific
mo model at any given moment. Oh yeah, I
do not think that so I didn't receive
enough feedback from philosophers of
science to know whether they receive
they they find these ideas
uh uh uh plausible but then again I I I
I
I don't think that
uh traditional realist
oralist would have any reason to like
these ideas
particularly and when saying traditional
realist and anteriorist I I I really do
not
of uh so sometimes this
uh uh this naive realist or anterialist
are mainly uh parts of dogmatic
philosophers that live in any of us
rather than any particular person. So
I'm not referring to any particular
person but to any philosopher or
intellectual that in any moment decides
to insist on some ideas in which I mean
some specific ideas or models that have
been the that have been the topic of
their work for a very long time. uh so
we used to invest in their ideas and
then at some point we become a bit too
dogmatic and try to defend them a bit
rapidly and and I think that free energy
principle provides a way when casting
philosophical commitments in terms of
free energy principle provides enough
flexibility
to be able to a bit lack on some of your
ideas when you think that you don't have
enough evidence or argumentation for
supporting them. At the same time, it
allows you to defend them vigorously
enough when you think that the weight of
the evidence and argumentation
uh varants investing investing enough
ontological and epistemological
commitments into those models and
theories. Did it make any sense? I mean,
what I was trying to say. Oh, clearly.
Yeah. I was just wondering what Daniel
you you you started the
institute in the
uh how many years now? Six.
Five. Yeah. So in those five years like
how would you see the free energy
principle stirring the pot? because
that's
essentially I think what I think 5 years
later it it at least does that in terms
of of of what what's between philosophy
and science.
Yeah. Well, both of you have been along
for the ride. We've had many fun points
in that adventure.
Um, I'll connect a quote from the book
to also some of the sort of
undergraduate and graduate type
philosophy of biology and epistemology
that that that I saw. And maybe this
speaks to how what Majid and others are
pointing towards gives us a a
a blended or more nuanced take. So this
is on page 87.
The central question is how can agency
theory which has an empiricist leaning
establish the truth value of
counterfactual statements. So I mean if
what's factual is actual and what's
actual is empirical and empiricism is
about describing the actual and deriving
justified true beliefs and all of that
kind of materialist realist everything
in that camp. Yet our actuality
includes counterfactuals and the
adjacent possible, the cognitive actual,
the expected free energy, the simulated
possibilities, you know, entertained or
virtualized
considerations as actual. So then in
response, this is continuing the quote.
I propose that the truth value of
counterfactual statements could be
grounded in factual information about
how sophisticated organisms which are
presumed to possess agency can model
their counterfactual expectations about
lawike stability in their environment.
And of course the the quote and the book
goes on. So, it's a cognitive realist
take, but as you kind of pointed out,
whether we're cognitive instrumentalist
or cognitive realist, that's not
necessarily even the axis that
separates. It's about an informed
cognitive scientific approach to
philosophy. So that there's the
philosophy of science and the science of
philosophy which is like pragmatism
which is okay there's cognition about
that inquiry. What is the temperature in
that room? And then there would be like
a meta-cience or pragmatism of a science
or some kind of nested layer about going
across and switching between different
inquiries.
some that are more data driven, some
that are more speculative or
axiomatically or ontologically driven.
But whether your ontology is from
another frame entirely
nonsensical, entirely whimsical, super
small, very
large,
heterogeneous, whatever kinds of
commitments it makes or whatever
commitments it commits to commit to
commit to make, however you want to
compose all those
possibilities, they are plain cognitive
embodied realities.
as well. And so that is kind of some of
the space of bringing in uh a
descriptive first showing up with a
posture and an openness, then a
descriptive analytical layer. Now moving
on through implementational and
computational methods to take it all the
way
through from just standing on the shore
of justified true belief like we're
going to use frequentist statistics.
We're gonna accept or reject binary
hypothesis and we're going to have an
epistemology that's based upon is this a
justified true belief or is this not a
justified true belief on through the
continual basian or metabasian
updating with all that it entails in
terms of probability densities and like
agentic realities.
So do you think both of you do you think
then when you kind of pick up the free
energy principle and you pick up active
inference and you pick up Mene's book is
is one of the should one of the
takeaways be don't get
stuck be able to sort of continually
update continue to be able to move back
and forth swing the the pendulum
and and not find
yourself getting in your own way or or
you know if you if you decide that you
want to pause for a moment that's fine
but but free energy principle agency
theory pragmatism together if you allow
it will create a virtuous vortex like I
I I'm I'm really curious about this
because you can spend lots and lots of
time sort of trying to figure out what
the jargon is and what people are
talking about. But isn't the lesson to
take
away don't get
stuck. I think that is sort of pointed
to and Majid maybe you could expand on
this chapter three rolling stones simple
and sophisticated. So other than the of
course cultural reference, what does it
mean that it's a rolling
stone, why did you put it in the uh
critical third position in the book to
break it down that way? All right, very
well. Uh
uh I'm going to make a a very small
remark on on the part of the books that
you quoted earlier and then I'm going to
relate that to uh the rolling stone. So
uh uh with regard to rolling a stone
sometimes I think that I have some title
in mind then I'm writing books and
papers about them but aside from that
let's return to the the the points that
you mentioned earlier about yeah uh
truth value of counterfactual so we we
usually let's just let let's see that in
this way and then I'm going to to
explain the relation to pragmatism and
the way that I see the situation and and
so uh there
causal claims, causality claims, claims
about what causes what. Right? So we
already decided consider let's assume
that we consider that we don't have any
uh any decisive answer about the
question of what causes what. We don't
have any firstand access to the causal
structure of the universe. So we can
decide that in a in in a dogmatic way
what is causing what. So the best thing
that we can do is to consider our
evidence about what is causing what and
then try to probabilistically work out
or notion of the causal network of the
events and so on. So seeing in that way
uh
counterfactual I mean having a notion of
counterfactual
uh relation between different things
provides a very uh
reliable source or resource for being
able to uh make some evaluation of of
the truth of causality claim. So I'm I'm
going to claim that for example if this
active we didn't have this conversation
in 2022 in this this active inference
lab session I was not going
to write that chapter for example and
this is a counterfactual claim how we
how would we be able to evaluate that
some people would try
to use sophisticated semantic tools such
as possible words and then decide the
truth value of these counterfactual
claims on the basis of their truths to
in all other words that are similar to
our own then the then there would be a
fascinating philosophical debate about
the reality of this possible world are
there real or there are they just unreal
and there are loads of there's tradeoff
of intuition about the reality of this
possible world so what I'm what I'm
suggesting here is uh in my own opinion
a more pragmatic down to earth solution
to just try to evaluate the truth value
of this counterfactual on the basis of
factual information that we have about
ourselves as some sort of
self-organizing systems that have
representation of the future
consequences of our actions or the or
the consequences of future courses of
action and evaluate them
counterfactually. So we have this
cognitive faculty and this is what
underlies our capacity to form
counterfactuals and in order to be able
to decide to justify the
objectivity of the way that we decide
the truth value of counterfactuals we
don't need to necessarily get engaged in
metaphysical debates about the reality
of possible world but just take a closer
look as how uh factual organism like
ourselves are engaging in this kind of
things. So from this perspective, all
that we need to pay attention to in
order to be able to deal with
sophisticated
uh philosophical questions around us and
this is the uh pragmatist layer of my
work is to to
to take a look at uh very simple or
sometimes sophisticated objects and
events around us such as rolling stones.
So uh we can learn so I so so the main
points of the third chapter. So this is
in fourth chapter where I speak about
modality and it builds on what I said
earlier in the third chapter of the book
about agency and how agents could be
modeled and what's the difference
between a simple rolling stone that just
come down from as as a physicalist as as
a as a rock that just rolls down uh
asleep or something and let's say a
sophisticated ated agent which is the
member of the band rolling a stone. So
in the first case the action of the
stone the the action of the rock is
simply determined by some uh external uh
factors some external trajectories the
weight the weight the angel the and so
on. With regard to the more
sophisticated
uh entity, a self-organizing system that
is capable of having some sort of
intrinsic action.
Uh the difference
is in the way that they are trying to
actually they don't try to I mean the
simple rolling stones the the simple
rocks don't try to do something they are
just some subject to some extrinsic
forces. what I'm trying to speak
metaphorically here. But so the
difference is that the f in the first
case the rock just rolls down the the
the the slope or the valley. The second
one is capable of choosing its path and
by when when we speak of choosing its
path then again uh we would be able to
explicate that in terms of the free
energy principle in terms of how this
self-organizing systems can represent
the future the consequences of their
action and make decision on the base of
that and
so and uh the point that I tried to
develop in the fourth chapter was just
building on that to explain or ways of
evaluating the truth value of
counterfactual events uh on the basis of
this cognitive capacity to uh to choose
amongst the
uh diverse paths of action on the basis
of one conception of their consequences.
So and and in my opinion it's a
pragmatist and
pragmatic approach to solving the the
the the question of evaluation of the
truth of counterfactual claims which are
totally necessary for being able to to
justify the the objectivity of the
truths that we assign to causality
claims.
Awesome. I can ask another question or
Dean, do you want to give any comments
on it? No, go. All right. So, one other
part to touch upon in the book near the
very end. I won't spoil the ending, but
in section 8.5 on page 175, you talk
about inculturation and AI. So again,
there's the whole section and there's
the whole discussion, but how did you
make the work timely and relevant? And
even in your own years of thinking about
this and exploring these topics, how
have you seen empirically the evolution
in our generative landscape? How h how
did those changes play into like how you
thought about and positioned the end of
the book there?
Oh, you're
muted. Yeah, very well. I mean, uh, a
part of it about artificial
intelligence. So, uh, the the third
chapter is about agency. We usually
think of agents as natural
self-organizing systems like ourselves.
uh but the projects of the book was to
go beyond intuition and try to
articulate agency in scientifically
plausible terms in terms of making
contactual as I say I I repeated it so
many times I'm not going to do that.
uh if this is the mark of agency, the
ability to form counteractual models of
the outcomes of the action in order to
choose the path of action that is
compatible with my desires and
expectations.
So does it need to be a human thing only
or could could also artificial systems
uh demonstrate some properties and
capacities that are related to
uh the capacity to form counterfactual
models and choose the
uh option between them that corresponds
to their expectation. So I think that to
some extent this is a
a difficult question because then we
have to consider what it means for an
artificial system to have desires and
expectations. But then again what we
know about desires and expectations in
terms of pre-energy principle uh is
basically specified in terms of the
uh uh the factors that eventually
contribute to maximizing the chance of
the sur. So it it goes back to
existential imperative of free energy
principle to speak about the factors
that contribute to maximize the chance
of the survival of the organism or the
species of the that of which the
organism is a representative. And there
is no reason to think that an artificial
system
uh can't cannot have
uh some desires in the sense that it
there is no no reason to think that an
artificial system shouldn't uh
shouldn't be able
to have expectations as to how
to increase is the chance of its
existence. So, uh I'm not claiming that
the present day artificial intelligence
systems are capable of doing that, but
uh I know that you are familiar with
this literature. So, the present
artificial intelligence systems are
basically specified by Priston and
colleagues as passive artificial
intelligence system. They already
started to think of active artificial
intelligence systems as systems that are
not uh just designed to be passive to
execute prompts that are uh fed to them
by an uh external agent.
as as artificial systems that are
capable of evolving in in a specific
environment and form their own
expectations
uh of the environment in in terms of
models of the environment and in terms
of
uh some prior beliefs about uh which
which aspects of this environment
contribute to increasing their chance of
existence. So assuming that there could
be some sort of artificial intelligent
sorry you you wanted
to you you wanted to say something
Daniel I thought no no
answer so I think that seeing this from
this perspective to seeing the mark of
agency as the capacity to I form
expectations about the consequences of
action and and peak up amongst them. uh
it provides some basis for being able to
also ascribe some level of agency to
artificial intelligence systems and then
I also see that in the context of
scientific practice. So human beings
were supposed to be agents scientist. So
when we started to speak of scientist
and philosopher in this talk we
basically had human beings in mind but
science is not an individual
uh project. Science is to some extent a
social institute in in in the sense that
what happens in science is a result of
collaboration between uh different
agents and this assuming that these
agents don't need to be only human
beings. Uh I think that
uh I think that
uh considering artificial artifacts as
agent that are capable of collaboration
with human being also has some
ramifications for
uh or or conception of scientific
practice as a social
uh as a social institute as something
that happens in the network of
collaboration between different entities
that are capable of engaging in
intellectual practices.
Thank you. Dean, do you have
any ways to take it? The only the only
thing that I can say in my defense, I
mean, if if what I say is sometimes a
bit incoherent, is that I f I I write
with far more clarity than I demonstrate
in my speaking.
We all
do.
Um, well, I I'm not I'm not your
uh I'm not your agent, but I I am I am
really uh impressed with what you were
able
to organize and and and cohhere. My my
takeaway from all of this is
you lots of times we hear people express
the desire to go beyond and I appreciate
that. Um but then there's a small
proportion of those people that have
that desire that actually get beyond. I
think that I think the nature of the of
the project you you know it's your book
now it's your baby.
um that ability to actually not just
hope to get beyond but actually do
depends on not getting stuck. I'm kind
of I'm kind of stuck on that idea of not
remaining static like keeping the active
and the active inference um
going. I think that the I think that the
book sets up a preparation space from
which wavefinding can originate. Now
waveinding is kind of my my baby. It's
the whole navigation journey aspect of
of trying to figure out what's going on.
Um I think I think that this work is
very complimentary to the idea of
agentic training because I hold the two
things up as being quite different. One
is more biased towards the exploratory
whereas the other is more biased to the
exploitive. And so my my kind of last
comment is is to both of you like when I
when I when I hold up or when I watch
some of the stuff that Daniel's doing in
the inferance series which I find
fascinating cuz I would say 80 to 90% of
it goes completely over my head. I don't
know exactly what's going on. And I and
I say that respectfully because I do
want to kind of figure out what's going
on there, which is I think a lot of work
that's done on the exploitive end of the
continuum. And then I read what you were
able to put together in terms of this
book, which I
think opens up the possibility of going
sort of trying to get trying to get
beyond not just wishing for it, but
actually doing it. I kind of wonder how
like to the person who's not the
originator of the book and not the
originator of the infrarance series how
how I can
triangle learn how I can triangulate off
both like how I can put those two policy
form formats into some sort of coherency
because I think together it would it
would like actually multiply the ability
to sort of resolve a lot of these
questions quicker. Maybe it might leave
things messy. It might be
like, you know, racing on a downhill
mountain bike and, you know, that takes
a certain amount takes a certain amount
of uh commitment, but I'd still like to
be able to figure out some way to be
able to put those two worlds together.
the one that you're you're working
through on the philosophical side that
and that and that how do we explore this
world of between and then the exploitive
side what's already been put out there
and how can we not how can we not take
advantage of that at the same time so
that that kind of ties in with with
Daniel's pointing at the AI thing cuz I
don't want to be a lite I don't want to
sort of run away from it because I don't
get it right away But at the same time,
I do I do find that the the barrier to
entry part of this and trying to put
those two worlds together is it's pretty
that's a pretty big wall to climb.
I'll give a short first thought and then
Majid you can you can give a a sort of
last last piece however you want to take
it out. So it it uh sort of resonated
with thinking about the the learners
paths, learning paths and and training
paths. And on the ontological level, we
could ask like how have advances in the
natural sciences led to changes in the
ways that we might want to skill in
natural sciences? Like should we still
be using the domains and journals and
disciplines and textbooks and
departments of the university or has
complex adaptive system studies or other
kinds of
approaches helped evolve on on the
ontological level what the topics are.
Now let's put that aside and focus on
the agentic
epistemology and that's like well now
seeing that just historically those
departments were functioning in a
frequentist justified true belief theory
of science
environment that was like which you'd
characterized as being about theories
and and with with all of these kind of
big topics underneath it and and not
that the departments caused the
epistemology or vice versa, but it was
part of a co-extant environment. So what
would be
um from a process perspective different
in the learner's
epistemology and how do
increasingly agentic learning resources
in the learner's niche influence their
pathtaking? when it goes from being like
I wonder if that book exists to okay the
book exists in the library lookup but
how will I get it to here's the book to
here's the custom generated book for me
right
now and that is getting more
agentic and so how does that change how
we train and and learn and skill
as highle investigators like the kind
who write synthetic books like
Majid, but
increasingly all kinds of
investigators and being able to dispatch
these multiscale inquiries like doing a
deep research search on perplexity or
other services. It is dispatching nested
sequences of agents in their inquiry and
that becomes part of your inquiry as
well.
[Music]
Very well. Very very well. I I I think
that I totally agree. So, uh
look, I think that this is a fine point
for the final note. So, I'm going to
make it like my also finalist statement.
So, uh as
organisms uh we like to keep the amount
of our free energy low, the amount of
our surprisal low. So, we do not like to
get surprised. And some people would say
that the best way of doing that is to
just stay in a cave and never leave the
room because it we wouldn't be surprised
at all so far as we stay here. But on
the other hand and this is the
exploitation part just to stay in your
environment just exploited and there
wouldn't be any surprise and I mean to a
first approximation to the known
initiated free energy principle might
look like that but then again there is
the uh exploration part and we don't
just survive by by sitting in a room we
need to go outside and try to explore on
the other hand just being a vendor and I
mean just going around doesn't
contribute to our surveal that much
enough. So the key is to uh strike the
balance between the right amount of
exploitation the right amount of sitting
in the room and the right amount of
exploration to and in order to be able
to survive we need to be able to strike
this balance. I mean just not go around
and spend all of your resources to
explore new possibly non-existent
resources and on the other hand don't
just spend all of your time to uh sit in
a sit in a small room. I think that it
also as a strategy and I think that it
is because we are basically
uh formed in this fashion. And we are
shaped in this. We are wired in this
passion. And there is no wonder that in
other or other aspects of our life too
such as in our research we
we our research would be maximally
optimal if we could strike the balance
between exploitation and exploration.
And I think that in general it also
applies to scientific progress. So there
are to to state that in terms of Thomas
uh theory of a structure of
scientific revolution. There are of
course paradigms nor that that that
capture the normal science that is
that's what's already there and it it it
gets orthodox and fashionable but
science would waste away and die if we
only stick the this kind of paradigms.
On the other hand there are luminaries
visionaries that go out and and and
speculate new possibilities and research
them and sometimes they stumble on new
things.
So uh I think that if science could
strike the balance between this
exploitation being conservative enough
and at the same time being innovative
enough there would have been copious
amount of scientific progress. I suspect
and I only suspect that because I think
that science is is something that is
done by scientists that are basically
self-organizing systems that are that
are in the business of striking the
balance between exploitation
exploration. No, sometimes I wonder as
an academic I wonder whether the present
science has invested too much in the
exploitation part and ignored
exploration uh at at at the risk of yeah
being a bit uh
uh I don't want to say stagnant or or or
a bit too orthodox but I think that if
science could strike that balance
possibly things would have in a more
progressive
uh I think that with this possibly with
this new changes I mean technological
developments and so on there should be
some further changes in scientific
institutes no one knows in which
direction it's going to spin whether it
will make the the life of academics
better or worse but I think that it will
contribute to the distributed nature of
science makes it even more distributed
make people to be able to access the
information in uh in in uh in a more cal
in a more collaborative manner and and
and they would be able to collaborate
more and more uh with progress of this
kind of uh technologies in the same way
that we could we could communicate and
collaborate and possibly it would lead
to development of new projects. So I'm
not necessarily pessimistic even though
there might be reasons for being
pessimistic about this new development
carrier-wise. I'm not that pessimistic
with regard to scientific progress so
far
as yeah it may bring about the chance of
striking the balance between traditional
conservative academic strategies and
more brave ex uh ex exploratory new ways
of finding the path of your research and
intellectual progress.
That's perfect. Yep.
Thank you again Majid for the awesome
book for Dean for the prep and the
annotations and let us look forward to
discussing again.
Thank you very much for inviting me. So
thanks to you this book is not a
steelborn which is a very very good
reason for me to celebrate. So and thank
you very very much for your kind words
and your your attention and your grace
and I thank our viewers for their
attention too. Thank you fellows.